<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

 <title>Joel Azevedo</title>
 <link href="http://www.iterativetechnologies.com/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
 <link href="http://www.iterativetechnologies.com/"/>
 <updated>2015-09-08T21:39:48-06:00</updated>
 <id>http://www.iterativetechnologies.com</id>
 <author>
   <name>Joel Azevedo</name>
   <email></email>
 </author>

 
 <entry>
   <title>Hybrid App Development</title>
   <link href="http://www.iterativetechnologies.com/2015/09/08/hybrid-cordova/"/>
   <updated>2015-09-08T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
   <id>http://www.iterativetechnologies.com/2015/09/08/hybrid-cordova</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I do not have as much experience in mobile development as I would like. Although I am very comfortable with responsive design using JS and CSS I want to dive deeper into mobile development. Since getting my MacBook I’ve spent a little time in Xcode and doing a couple of ‘hello world’ things and playing with Swift but nothing too serious. I’ve heard Ionic and Cordova mentioned a few times lately and so I’m going to take a look. I’ll probably continue to learn some of the native Swift/Objective-C/Java features, but given how much fun Javascript has been lately going with a hybrid solution just seems good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1&gt;What is Cordova?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cordova exposes many of the native device features through Javascript APIs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://cordova.apache.org/docs/en/5.0.0/guide_overview_index.md.html#Overview&quot;&gt;Apache Cordova&lt;/a&gt; is an open-source mobile development framework. It allows you to use standard web technologies such as HTML5, CSS3, and JavaScript for cross-platform development, avoiding each mobile platforms&amp;#39; native development language. Applications execute within wrappers targeted to each platform, and rely on standards-compliant API bindings to access each device&amp;#39;s sensors, data, and network status.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h1&gt;Getting Cordova&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To install Cordova all you need to have is &lt;a href=&quot;https://nodejs.org/&quot;&gt;Node.js&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-bash&quot; data-lang=&quot;bash&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;$ &lt;/span&gt;sudo npm install -g cordova&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h1&gt;Create the App&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-bash&quot; data-lang=&quot;bash&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;$ &lt;/span&gt;cordova create iterative com.iterative.hello HelloWorld&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This will generate the skeleton project in a directory called iterative. The second and third arguments are optional. The second argument is an identifier and the third is the applications display title.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1&gt;Add the iOS platform&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-bash&quot; data-lang=&quot;bash&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;$ &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;cd &lt;/span&gt;iterative &lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;#make sure you are in the directory&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;$ &lt;/span&gt;cordova platform add ios&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You could also do android, windows8, etc...&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-bash&quot; data-lang=&quot;bash&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;$ &lt;/span&gt;cordova platform add amazon-fireos
&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;$ &lt;/span&gt;cordova platform add android
&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;$ &lt;/span&gt;cordova platform add blackberry10
&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;$ &lt;/span&gt;cordova platform add firefoxos&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/public/images/8705FB8C-A532-4D0E-88D8-8AA55C9A3C0F.png&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot&quot; title=&quot;Screenshot&quot;&gt;
Looks like the iOS folder is created with all of the necessary setup files.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/public/images/F50E7D30-E4E0-4DCA-B447-2FD2E2226DFB.png&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot&quot; title=&quot;Screenshot&quot;&gt;
This is the project opened in Xcode. The www directory contains the stuff I am most curious about: the HTML/CSS/JS. I’m going to go ahead a make a couple of small changes: replace logo.png with my own and put in some different text. Small changes but just to see if it picks them up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1&gt;Build the App&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-bash&quot; data-lang=&quot;bash&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;$ &lt;/span&gt;cordova build&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This will compile everything from the www directory to the specific platform. If I make any changes to the www files, as I did, you just need to run this again to compile it down the platform specific folders.
Now I can either jump back into Xcode and click Run or do this&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-bash&quot; data-lang=&quot;bash&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;$ &lt;/span&gt;cordova emulate&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/public/images/79B7F8A7-0D62-4366-82E2-17399D127DC5.png&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot&quot; title=&quot;Screenshot&quot;&gt;
And here is my new Cordova App running in the iOS simulator.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is surprisingly simple to get up and running with Cordova. Just getting this far in such a short amount of time has made me far less intimidated with rich mobile development. I&amp;#39;m looking forward to Ionic!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1&gt;Links&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://cordova.apache.org/&quot;&gt;Cordova&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://cordova.apache.org/docs/en/3.4.0/guide_cli_index.md.html#The%20Command-Line%20Interface&quot;&gt;The Command-Line Interface (CLI)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/Dn771545.aspx&quot;&gt;Getting Started with Visual Studio Tools for Apache Cordova&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Post Zero</title>
   <link href="http://www.iterativetechnologies.com/2015/09/07/post-0/"/>
   <updated>2015-09-07T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
   <id>http://www.iterativetechnologies.com/2015/09/07/post-0</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The beginning is the most important part of the work.&lt;br/&gt;
-Plato&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;m creating a blog in Jekyll on a MacBook Pro. I did not think 8 months ago that I would enjoy working on a Mac...ever. But what do you know, I like the Mac. I also like my Windows 10 box. I even installed Ubuntu in a VM a few weeks ago but that one has not lasted, I haven&amp;#39;t logged into it since the first day. I like technology and I like learning. I can&amp;#39;t imagine anyone being in this field of software development and not consider themselves a lifetime learner. I am not a genius by any stretch of the imagination but I enjoy sitting down and approaching problems from many different view points.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given my poor writing skills and extreme perfectionism I cannot image this blog will see too much attention but who knows.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 

</feed>
